<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-06-17T18:50:29+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/</id><title type="html">bb</title><subtitle>Take a moment to describe yourself</subtitle><entry><title type="html">\phi\mu</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/music%20vuilbak/2018/04/30/phimu.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="\phi\mu" /><published>2018-04-30T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-04-30T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/music%20vuilbak/2018/04/30/phimu</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/music%20vuilbak/2018/04/30/phimu.html">&lt;p&gt;Better known as &lt;a href=&quot;https://bruinebeer.bandcamp.com/album/-&quot;&gt;φμ&lt;/a&gt; when unicode works or $\phi\mu$ if we want to do fancy math style. Previously (in earlier versions) also known as ‘&lt;a href=&quot;https://bruinebeer.bandcamp.com/album/-&quot;&gt;Generative music for sleeping&lt;/a&gt;’ (or more informally even &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;orthosong&lt;/code&gt;). Whatever the name, it is a work I made in 2016 and edited and expanded in the last months of 2017 and is an exploration in the world of generative music and unedited long-duration field recording. As some of the earlier titles already indicate, it can be considered as music for sleeping, or at least as music with some sleep-inducing qualities. I am particularly fond of this music as a matter of fact, and while many might think it is way lamer than previous things I made, I might consider it as my best work (wherever that might end up on some external reference scale). It was presented during an exhibition in the art gallery ‘Galerij Jan Colle’ in Ghent during an exhibition entitled ‘Waar de vogeltjes fluiten’, curated by Charlotte Vandenbroucke.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/phimu2.jpg &quot; width=&quot;49.8%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/phimu.jpg &quot; width=&quot;49.8%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have written about the underlying generative model, which is based on multiple sequence alignments of sets of evolutionary related genes (better known as &lt;em&gt;gene families&lt;/em&gt;), before and will not reiterate these technical details here. I include the accompanying note for the exhibition here and point to my bandcamp page for the actual music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This music was generated based on sets of evolutionary related gene sequences across different plant species. This synthetic result was merged with field recordings made on travels during the summers of 2016 and 2017 to form an organic whole. The music embodies the paradoxical goal of purposelessness. It evokes tranquility and peaceful indifference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;iframe style=&quot;border: 0; width: 100%; height: 120px;&quot; src=&quot;https://bandcamp.com/EmbeddedPlayer/album=2504424009/size=large/bgcol=ffffff/linkcol=0687f5/tracklist=false/artwork=small/transparent=true/&quot; seamless=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://bruinebeer.bandcamp.com/album/-&quot;&gt;φμ by Bruine Beer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Better known as φμ when unicode works or $\phi\mu$ if we want to do fancy math style. Previously (in earlier versions) also known as ‘Generative music for sleeping’ (or more informally even orthosong). Whatever the name, it is a work I made in 2016 and edited and expanded in the last months of 2017 and is an exploration in the world of generative music and unedited long-duration field recording. As some of the earlier titles already indicate, it can be considered as music for sleeping, or at least as music with some sleep-inducing qualities. I am particularly fond of this music as a matter of fact, and while many might think it is way lamer than previous things I made, I might consider it as my best work (wherever that might end up on some external reference scale). It was presented during an exhibition in the art gallery ‘Galerij Jan Colle’ in Ghent during an exhibition entitled ‘Waar de vogeltjes fluiten’, curated by Charlotte Vandenbroucke.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Non-particular dream</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/music%20vuilbak%20bruinebeer/2018/04/30/npd.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Non-particular dream" /><published>2018-04-30T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-04-30T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/music%20vuilbak%20bruinebeer/2018/04/30/npd</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/music%20vuilbak%20bruinebeer/2018/04/30/npd.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://bruinebeer.bandcamp.com/album/non-particular-dream&quot;&gt;These tracks&lt;/a&gt; have been laying around for quite a while, and I have always  enjoyed them myself. However they have only been released in the most obscure places: there was this vuilbak compilation cassette called ‘Stort Vol.2’, which was a limited edition release of size 3 (a threefold increase compared to Stort Vol.1!), and one of the tracks could be found somewhere on the &lt;a href=&quot;www.vuilbak.in&quot;&gt;vuilbak record-label website&lt;/a&gt;. Now these are collected under the title &lt;em&gt;Non-particular dream&lt;/em&gt;. In the words of the great composer:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“For those who love such things, and in particular for those who are familiar with comparable work, for the delight of their souls”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/npd.jpg &quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">These tracks have been laying around for quite a while, and I have always enjoyed them myself. However they have only been released in the most obscure places: there was this vuilbak compilation cassette called ‘Stort Vol.2’, which was a limited edition release of size 3 (a threefold increase compared to Stort Vol.1!), and one of the tracks could be found somewhere on the vuilbak record-label website. Now these are collected under the title Non-particular dream. In the words of the great composer:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Recap - finite populations</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/qgen%20popgen%20evolution%20recap/2018/04/30/finite_populations.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Recap - finite populations" /><published>2018-04-30T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-04-30T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/qgen%20popgen%20evolution%20recap/2018/04/30/finite_populations</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/qgen%20popgen%20evolution%20recap/2018/04/30/finite_populations.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;finite-idealized-population&quot;&gt;Finite idealized population&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A bit of a recap is never a bad thing to do. So considering a locus with two alleles $p$ and $q$ in a finite diploid population of size $N$, initially at frequencies $q_0$ and $p_0$. Assuming an idealized population, following all Hardy-Weinberg conditions except the infinite population size, the expected frequency of $q_1$ is then $q_0$. The variance of this quantity can be calculated as a binomial sampling variance with sample size of $2N$ and is given by:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\sigma^2_{q_1} = \frac{q_0 (1-q_0)}{2N}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This can be interpreted as the variance in $q_1$ among different samples of size $N$ drawn from a base population with $q = q_0$. This is also the variance of the &lt;em&gt;change&lt;/em&gt; in allele frequency $\sigma^2_{\Delta q}$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can also consider &lt;strong&gt;genotype frequencies&lt;/strong&gt;, where the frequency of homozygotes in generation $t$ is of course given by $q_{t-1}^2$ and $p_{t-1}^2$. Consider the mean frequency of homozygotes among lines sampled from a base population with minor allele frequency $q_0$, which can be denoted $\overline{q^2}$. Recall that the expression for the variance of a random variable $X$ is given by $E(X^2) - E(X)^2$. Thus we have:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
\begin{eqnarray}
\sigma^2_{q} &amp;=&amp; \overline{q^2} - \overline{q}^2 \\
\overline{q^2} &amp;=&amp; \overline{q}^2 + \sigma^2_{q}
\end{eqnarray} %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consequences of this expression are clear. Indeed, $\overline{q}$ is just given by $q_0$, &lt;em&gt;i.e.&lt;/em&gt; the allele frequency in the base population. So the expected number of homozygotes $\overline{q^2}$ is always in excess over the original fraction of homozygotes $q_0^2$. Likewise, the fraction of heterozygotes is reduced by $2\sigma^2_{q}$. Note that we have not considered the process in function of time. We have just observed a snapshot situation in a finite population and have related it to the base population from which it was originally drawn. By doing this we observed that the fraction of homozygotes is increased with the variance of the allele frequency $\sigma_q^2$. How $\sigma_q^2$ evolves with time is something we will consider next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;inbreeding&quot;&gt;Inbreeding&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will now consider the famous coefficient of inbreeding, which is a measure of the dispersive process happening in finite populations. The coefficient of inbreeding $F$ is the probability that two alleles at a randomly sampled locus are &lt;em&gt;identical by descent&lt;/em&gt; (IBD). The average $F$ gives a measure of genetic drift in a population. Note that $F$ is only meaningful when compared to a base population!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Considering a base population with $2N$ genes which we consider all to be independent. We can easily see that $ F_1 = \frac{1}{2N} $. Similarly, we can reason that&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;F_2 = \frac{1}{2N} + (1 - \frac{1}{2N})F_1&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This gives a recursion for $F$. However this recursion is as such not very easy to work with. We can easily see that there is always an addition of $\frac{1}{2N}$ to the inbreeding coefficient in subsequent generations, originating from the probability to sample identical alleles in the base population. Call this $\Delta F = \frac{1}{2N}$. Now we can write the following expression&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;F_{t} = \Delta F + (1 -\Delta F)F_{t-1}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;which can be rearranged to give&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\Delta F = \frac{F_{t} - F_{t-1}}{1-F_{t-1}}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;which clearly shows the nature of $\Delta F$ as a measure for the rate of inbreeding. Indeed, it expresses the increase in the inbreeding coefficient normalized by the proportion of the population that was not yet inbred.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We now define the panmictic index $P_t = 1-F_t$ and we rearrange the last expression to give&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\frac{P_t}{P_{t-1}} = 1-\Delta F&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;which gives rise to a lovely recursion rendering&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
\begin{eqnarray}
\frac{P_t}{P_{t-2}} = \frac{P_t}{P_{t-1}} \frac{P_{t-1}}{P_{t-2}} &amp;=&amp; (1-\Delta F)^2 \\
&amp;\vdots&amp; \\
P_t &amp;=&amp; (1 - \Delta F)^t
\end{eqnarray} %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which allows us to get a general expression for $F$ in function of $t$&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;F_t = 1 - (1-\Delta F)^t&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;which holds of course only when the F_0 is considered as 0.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can now revisit the expressions in the previous sections which were attained by considering properties of binomial samples. We have shown that $\sigma_{\Delta q}^2 = \frac{q_0(1-q_0)}{2N}$ which we can now express as $q_0(1-q_0)\Delta F = q_0p_0\Delta F$. Similarly we can consider the variance in gene frequencies among different hypothetical lines of a same base population in any generation as $\sigma_{q,t}^2 = q_0p_0F_t$. Whereas $\Delta F$ can be regarded as the rate of new inbreeding, $F_t$ is a measure of the accumulated effect of random drift over $t$ generations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can again consider genotype frequencies. The mean fraction of homozygotes across hypothetical lines of size $2N$ of a same base population is still given by&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\overline{q^2} = \overline{q}^2 + \sigma_q^2&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where $\sigma_q^2$ can now be expressed in terms of the base population frequencies and the number of generations! Indeed, we have:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\overline{q^2} = q_0^2 + q_0p_0F_t&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This clearly shows the cumulating excess of homozygotes through inbreeding. Similarly, we can consider the decline in the fraction heterozygotes ($H$). Given $H_0 = 2p_0q_0$ we can see that&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
\begin{eqnarray}
H_t &amp;=&amp; 2p_0q_0 - 2q_0p_0F_t \\
    &amp;=&amp; 2p_0q_0(1-F_t) \\
    &amp;=&amp; H_0(1-F_t) = H_0P_t
\end{eqnarray} %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;since the homozygote excess occurs at the expense of heterozygotes. Interestingly, this provides an interpretation for the panmictic index as the proportional decrease in the fraction of heterozygotes relative to the base population.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is I think the core theory of inbreeding and basic population genetics in finite populations which one should always be able to reproduce on demand.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Finite idealized population</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Allele surfing</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/qgen%20popgen%20evolution%20journalclub/2018/04/29/allele_surfing.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Allele surfing" /><published>2018-04-29T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-04-29T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/qgen%20popgen%20evolution%20journalclub/2018/04/29/allele_surfing</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/qgen%20popgen%20evolution%20journalclub/2018/04/29/allele_surfing.html">&lt;p&gt;Continuing my lonely journal club, I stumbled on this paper today:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Gilbert, K.J., Sharp, N.P., Angert, A.L., Conte, G.L., Draghi, J.A., Guillaume, F., Hargreaves, A.L., Matthey-Doret, R., Whitlock, M.C., 2018.
Local Adaptation Interacts with Expansion Load during Range Expansion: Maladaptation Reduces Expansion Load.
The American Naturalist 189, no 4
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And as I am quite interested in the population genetics of local adaptation and adaptation to climate change I took a look. While reading, an interesting concept previously unknown to me (or at least the term to describe it was unknown to me) was discussed, for which the term ‘&lt;strong&gt;allele surfing&lt;/strong&gt;’ has been coined (Klopfstein &lt;em&gt;et al.&lt;/em&gt; 2006). Quoting Gilbert &lt;em&gt;et al.&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“[…] This leads to the process of allele surfing (Klopfstein &lt;em&gt;et al.&lt;/em&gt; 2006), whereby a deleterious mutation that arises at the range edge is more likely to drift to high frequency than it would if it arose in the denser core of the species range. Because selection is inefficient, strongly deleterious alleles may persist and reach higher frequencies than expected in a population at equilibrium (Peischl and Excoffier 2015). Theoretical work shows that allele surfing is the main cause of increased deleterious allele frequency within recently expanded populations (Excoffier &lt;em&gt;et al.&lt;/em&gt; 2009). The reduction in fitness due to the accumulation of these deleterious alleles is termed expansion load (Peischl &lt;em&gt;et al.&lt;/em&gt; 2013; Peischl and Excoffier 2015).”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This statement connects the process of allele surfing to the concept of &lt;strong&gt;expansion load&lt;/strong&gt;, which might affect a population when undergoing range displacement as a response to environmental change. Indeed, while tracking its climatic optimum, a population resists global extinction but induces successive founder events, with a smaller effective population size in the newly entered range and stronger drift as a result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The paper by Gilbert &lt;em&gt;et al.&lt;/em&gt; is concerned with the interplay of this process with the problem of genetic swamping, which I have examined to quite some extent before. This is the process whereby maladaptive gene flow from the more populous center of the species’ range counteracts (‘swamps’) local adaptation at the range margins. This process can also be viewed in terms of load as a ‘migrational load’. How do the combined effects of maladaptive gene flow (causing migrational load) and allele surfing (causing expansion load) affect a population that is expanding (or displacing)? These are the questions addressed by Gilbert &lt;em&gt;et al.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another cool paper on allele surfing and expansion load is the following&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Peischl, S., Kirkpatrick, M., Excoffier, L., 2015.
Expansion Load and the Evolutionary Dynamics of a Species Range.
The American Naturalist 185, E81–E93. https://doi.org/10.1086/680220
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In which they have a real cool figure of surfing alleles in asexual populations!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Continuing my lonely journal club, I stumbled on this paper today:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The infinitesimal model</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/qgen%20popgen%20evolution/2018/02/24/infmodel.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The infinitesimal model" /><published>2018-02-24T16:04:50+01:00</published><updated>2018-02-24T16:04:50+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/qgen%20popgen%20evolution/2018/02/24/infmodel</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/qgen%20popgen%20evolution/2018/02/24/infmodel.html">&lt;p&gt;Barton, Etheridge &amp;amp; Véber (2017) have given us a nice and in-depth paper on the infinitesimal model in quantitative genetics, and discuss its very interesting possibilities in evolutionary genetics. Here I document a reading of this paper, mostly reproducing their math with some additional notes and comments. I do this kind of stuff as exercises, basically to become more fluent in mathematical aspects of evolutionary biology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-basic-infinitesimal-model&quot;&gt;The basic infinitesimal model&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We assume a large outcrossing population, and a purely additive quantitative trait with phenotype $z$, determined only by a genetic component for now. Denote $z_{ij}$ as the phenotype of offspring of a cross of parents $i$ and $j$ then&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;z_{ij} \sim N(\bar{z}_{i,j}, V_0)&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;i.e.&lt;/em&gt; the offspring phenotype follows a Normal distribution around the mean of the parents phenotypes with fixed variance $V_0$ independent of the parental phenotypes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under random mating, this implies that the distribution of trait values of population as a whole converges to a Normal distribution with variance $2V_0$. If we denote the variance of $z$ in the parental population as $V_1$, the variance of the offspring is given by $\frac{V_1}{2}$. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sum_of_normally_distributed_random_variables&quot;&gt;Bienaymé formula&lt;/a&gt; states that the variance of the sum of $n$ uncorrelated random variables is just the sum of the variances. Under random mating the parental phenotypes are just two uncorrelated random variables with variance $V_1$, the variance of the offspring trait value (which is just the mean of the parental values) is thus given by&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;Var(\bar{z}_{i,j}) = Var\Big(\frac{1}{2}(z_i + z_j)\Big) = \frac{1}{4}Var(z_i + z_j) = \frac{1}{4}2V_1 = \frac{V_1}{2}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The variance in the offspring generation is thus&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;V_1' = \frac{V_1}{2} + V_0&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where the first term cn be seen as the within family ariance, and the second as the between family variance. At equilibrium, where $V_1’ = V_1$, $V_1$ is given by&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
\begin{eqnarray}
\frac{V_1}{2} + V_0 &amp;=&amp; V_1  \\
                V_1 &amp;=&amp; 2V_0 \\
\end{eqnarray} %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means that half of the variance is &lt;em&gt;between&lt;/em&gt; families and half &lt;em&gt;within&lt;/em&gt; families (this can be seen when substituting $V_1$ for $2V_0$ in the expression for $V_1’$ above).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So in summary, under the basic, phenotypically defined, infinitesimal model the phenotypic value of offspring is distributed around the parental midpoint with fixed variance independent of the parental phenotypes. The model converges to a state where the total variance is distributed equally over between and within family variance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;selection&quot;&gt;Selection&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When selection is operating on the trait value (&lt;em&gt;i.e.&lt;/em&gt; the trait is correlated with relative fitness), arbitrary distributions of trait values can form. However the within-family trait value distributions will remain Gaussian! This seems to be a key property of the infinitesimal model, which Barton &lt;em&gt;et al.&lt;/em&gt; like to stress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;inbreeding&quot;&gt;Inbreeding&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Barton &lt;em&gt;et al.&lt;/em&gt; next discuss how to incorporate inbreeding in what is now a purely phenotypically defined model. They stress that this still does not require any modern insights in ‘genes’, and that in theory only inbreeding coefficients ($F_{i,j}$) are required which can be estimated from pedigrees. However, for ease of explanation they proceed using modern terminology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the current model, the expected value of the offspring is the midpoint of the parental trait values. Variation between siblings is induced by random segregation during meiosis. The variance induced by segregation is obviously reduced when the parental genomes are similar, this is of course to say that there is inbreeding if parents are not unrelated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For haploid individuals $i$ and $j$, the relationship, derived from a pedigree is described by $F_{i,j}$, which is the probability of identity by descent (IBD) of two genes from these individuals. The variance among offspring of these two parental haploid individuals is just $V_0(1-F_{i,j})$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a diploid individual, meiosis induces segregation variance among gametes proportional to $(1-F_{i,i})$, with $F_{i,i}$ the probability that two genes of a diploid pair are IBD. To form a gamete in individual $i$, we start with two independently sampled ancestral genes within the diploid individual, with variance among these $2V_0$ (since the variance of the sum of two uncorrelated random variables is just the sum of their variances) and probability of IBD $F_{i,i}$. &lt;em&gt;I am not fully sure about the following derivation&lt;/em&gt; (and also not if the notation is sound), but when meisosis forms 4 gametes, with mean phenotype $\bar{z}_{i,i}$ the corresponding variance should be something like this&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
\begin{eqnarray}
Var(\bar{z_{i,i}}) &amp;=&amp; Var\Big(\frac{1}{4}\sum_{j=1}^{4}z_{i,i,j}\Big) \\
                   &amp;=&amp; \frac{\sum_{j=1}^{4}Var(z_{i,i})}{4^2} \\
                   &amp;=&amp; \frac{4Var(z_{i,i})}{4^2} \\
                   &amp;=&amp; \frac{1}{4}2V_0 \\
\end{eqnarray} %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;conditioning on the genes sampled not being IBD. This gives an overall segregational variance for a mating of diploid parent $i$ and $j$ described by&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\frac{1}{4}(1-F_{i,i})2V_0 + \frac{1}{4}(1-F_{j,j})2V_0 =
V_0\Bigg(1 - \frac{(F_{i,i} + F_{j,j})}{2}\Bigg)&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where the possibility of IBD has been incorporated. At this moment, Barton &lt;em&gt;et al.&lt;/em&gt; note that the infinitesimal is now defined in terms of a constant genetic variance $V_0$ and a matrix of giving the probability of IBD for every individual. The probability of IBD is given by a set of recursion equations driven by a &lt;em&gt;pedigree matrix&lt;/em&gt; $P_{i,k}(t)$ which gives the probability that a gene $i$ came from parent $k$ in generation $t$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Barton, N. H., Etheridge, A. M., &amp;amp; Véber, A. (2017). The infinitesimal model: Definition, derivation, and implications. Theoretical Population Biology, 118, 50–73. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tpb.2017.06.001&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Barton, Etheridge &amp;amp; Véber (2017) have given us a nice and in-depth paper on the infinitesimal model in quantitative genetics, and discuss its very interesting possibilities in evolutionary genetics. Here I document a reading of this paper, mostly reproducing their math with some additional notes and comments. I do this kind of stuff as exercises, basically to become more fluent in mathematical aspects of evolutionary biology.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Levin’s MCE model</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/polyploidy/popgen/2018/02/24/levin75.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Levin's MCE model" /><published>2018-02-24T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-02-24T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/polyploidy/popgen/2018/02/24/levin75</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/polyploidy/popgen/2018/02/24/levin75.html">&lt;p&gt;In his 1975 paper, Donald Levin proposed the first model of polyploid population establishment. Polyploidy was already for some time acknowledged as a feature of evolutionary interest in botany, but to my knowledge, Levin was the first to provide a (simple) mathematical description of the problem of cytotype coexistence. The model is inspired by population genetics, but instead of following alleles in a population, cytotypes (specifically diploids &amp;amp; tetraploids) are followed. Important to note is that Levin did not consider formation of tetraploids.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Levin models two coexisting cytotypes which undergo random mating (with some degree of selfing). Inter-cytotype matings are assumed to lead to inviable and infertile offspring. In Levin’s model, the proportion of the two cytotypes are denoted as $p$ and $q$. The frequency of within-cytotype matings is given by $p^2$ for the first cytotype and $q^2$ for the second cytotype. The frequency of between-cytotype matings is of course $2pq$. To see the strong frequency dependent effect under this model, consider the proportion of failed matings for each cytotype, given by $\frac{2pq}{p} = 2q = 2(1-p)$ for the first cytotype and analogously by $2p$ for the second cytotype. The main observation is thus that &lt;em&gt;the proportion of failed matings increases for lower population sizes&lt;/em&gt;, which Levin called the minority cytotype disadvantage, leading to minority cytotype exclusion (MCE).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed after one generation, the frequency of the first cytotype is given by $p’ = \frac{p^2}{p^2 + q^2}$, giving a change in cytotype proportion of&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
\begin{eqnarray}
\Delta p &amp;=&amp; \frac{p^2}{p^2 + q^2} - p \\
         &amp;=&amp; \frac{p^2q - q^2p}{p^2 + q^2} \\
\end{eqnarray} %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and likewise $ \Delta q = \frac{q^2p - p^2q}{p^2 + q^2} = -\Delta p $. This clearly shows how the minority cytotype disadvantage leads to minority cytotype exclusion. This is illustrated in the following plot:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/levinmce_1.png &quot; width=&quot;400px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Levin further incorporates selfing. With selfing probability $s$, the proportion of successful matings of course increases to $p^2(1-s) + ps$ (why not $p^2(1-s)^2 + ps$?). The above expressions can be adjusted for selfing as follows&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\Delta p = \frac{p^2(1-s) + ps}{p^2(1-s) + s + q^2(1-s)} - p&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think (note that $ps + qs = (p+q)s = s$).&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">In his 1975 paper, Donald Levin proposed the first model of polyploid population establishment. Polyploidy was already for some time acknowledged as a feature of evolutionary interest in botany, but to my knowledge, Levin was the first to provide a (simple) mathematical description of the problem of cytotype coexistence. The model is inspired by population genetics, but instead of following alleles in a population, cytotypes (specifically diploids &amp;amp; tetraploids) are followed. Important to note is that Levin did not consider formation of tetraploids.</summary></entry></feed>